<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Alex Strick van Linschoten</title>
<link>https://alexstrick.com/personal.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://alexstrick.com/personal.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Personal and technical writings from Alex Strick van Linschoten</description>
<generator>quarto-1.8.27</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2025 23:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>First stitches: on learning to knit</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Strick van Linschoten</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2025-01-05-first-stitches-on-learning-to-knit.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I previously learned how to crochet. I never made anything too fancy or intricate but it was an easy way to make beautiful presents for special occasions or individuals. This past christmas we decided that presents could only be exchanged if they were handmade. Cue: hours of double crochet to make <a href="https://www.ravelry.com/projects/strickvl/devotion-jumper">a jumper</a>, <a href="https://www.ravelry.com/projects/strickvl/cherish-snood">a snood</a> and some embroidery of <a href="https://www.folkglory.com/shop/p/palestine-ramallah-embroidery-kit">Ramallah <em>tatreez</em> patterns</a>. Along the way I discovered Elise’s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@purlsbeforethyme.">Purls Before Thyme channel</a> over on YouTube, devoured all the videos and got the idea that maybe I might want to try knitting.</p>
<p>What follows is mostly some self-reflection on some of the first practice swatches I made as part of <a href="https://tkga.org/">The Knitting Guild Association</a> (TKGA)’s <a href="https://tkga.org/education/correspondence-courses/">Learn to Knit correspondence course</a>. I also want a bit of a record of my progress since <a href="https://ravelry.com/">Ravelry</a> isn’t really a place for logging swatches.</p>
<section id="knits-and-purls" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="knits-and-purls">Knits and Purls</h2>
<p>The first thing I did was learn knit stitches and purls. With this swatch I just put in a bunch of repetition. I didn’t have any context beyond the specific stitches, in other words how these stitches fit together or what they were called.</p>
<p><img src="https://alexstrick.com/personal/images/2025-01-05-first-stitches-on-learning-to-knit/9c2c5e74dee5_F32BE84C-1F96-4478-BDD5-9E5D9EC9231A.avif" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Along the way there were a few places, especially at the beginning, where I accidentally increased or decreased the number of stitches. I was quite happy with how it turned out, this being basically the first thing I’ve ever knit.</p>
<p>It took me ages to summon up the courage to figure out how to purl, but once I’d done it a few times it wasn’t too hard.</p>
</section>
<section id="garter-stockinette" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="garter-stockinette">Garter &amp; stockinette</h2>
<p>I did two small swatches of garter stitch and stockinette:</p>
<p><img src="https://alexstrick.com/personal/images/2025-01-05-first-stitches-on-learning-to-knit/c7f2ca2ac92a_IMG_5738.avif" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Note how the garter stitch doesn’t curl at the edges. That’s a characteristic of the pattern, as I learned! (And vice versa for the stockinette swatch).</p>
<p>The yellow-ish yarn I used for this was <a href="https://www.ravelry.com/people/strickvl/stash/cool-merino">Lana Grossa Cool Merino</a> which is bound or woven (?) in a sort of chain as its internal structure. This means it doesn’t split, but it <em>does</em> offer many small holes that you might accidentally end up passing your needle through. Lesson learned!</p>
</section>
<section id="single-and-double-rib" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="single-and-double-rib">Single and Double Rib</h2>
<p>I switched to <a href="https://www.ravelry.com/people/strickvl/stash/drops-karisma-2">Drops Karisma</a> for the remaining swatches. Much easier, if fairly slippery on my metal (circular) needles. Both single and double ribs came together really easily and felt satisfying to produce.</p>
<p><img src="https://alexstrick.com/personal/images/2025-01-05-first-stitches-on-learning-to-knit/a82467b53d1e_A54D43C9-6215-4DAA-9188-B420444CA71E.avif" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>You can see that the bottom, where I cast on, is a bit uneven. I found previous swatches <em>extremely</em> tightly bound so I just used two needles together when casting on. This loosened things up considerably but seems to have had the unwanted side effect of making this wonky first row / edge.</p>
<p>I spoke with a friend (thanks Naheed!) and she suggested I try the old Norwegian cast on. This is AKA the twisted German cast on. It’s a variation of the long-tail cast on that I’d previously been using. It took a while to get the hang of but in the end it was not so complicated in the end. It’s what I’ve been using since then.</p>
<p>The TGKA course requires me to use the long-tail cast on so I’ll have to figure it out. The other alternative suggestion that people often have when your cast on is tight is to use a needle size one larger for the cast on. My interchangeable needles require a different base / connector for the next size up, so I’m not exactly sure in my head how this will all work.</p>
<p><img src="https://alexstrick.com/personal/images/2025-01-05-first-stitches-on-learning-to-knit/76c386664010_IMG_5748.avif" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>With the double ribs you can see that the base / cast on row is so much neater. Though now I’m starting to look at the right and left edges and wondering how those undulations can be reduced (or if it’s meant to be this way at all?).</p>
</section>
<section id="seed-stitch" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="seed-stitch">Seed stitch</h2>
<p>This seed stitch swatch proved trickier than expected although I learned some lessons along the way.</p>
<p><img src="https://alexstrick.com/personal/images/2025-01-05-first-stitches-on-learning-to-knit/dc63a397c05e_IMG_5752.avif" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>As you can see below, part of the swatch has what looks like some descending stockinette (or I’m not exactly sure what to call it). While doing the work I got confused as to whether I had to knit or to purl. The instruction was to do the opposite of whatever was on the stitch I was at (so knit if I saw a purl bump and so on), but this meant that I somehow ended up perpetuating mistakes I’d made on a previous row. In the end the only way to get out of it was to just stick to something regardless of what I’d done in the previous row.</p>
<p>I also found myself often getting into extremely tough and tight spots, where the tension was almost unmanageable. At first I was a bit confused as to the source of the problem, but I think (working hypothesis) that it is how loose my hands are and how loose the feeding or working yarn is. When I keep my hands loose and I actively work to keep the feeding yarn free, that seemed to improve things. But it often felt like I was being haunted by the ghosts of decisions past, where some tight knitting of a previous row would resurface and I’d have to deal with it in the next row even if my hands were much looser.</p>
</section>
<section id="increases-decreases-and-yarnovers" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="increases-decreases-and-yarnovers">Increases, decreases and yarnovers</h2>
<p>The final swatch includes multiple different techniques and somehow it’s the least obviously successful of the lot.</p>
<p><img src="https://alexstrick.com/personal/images/2025-01-05-first-stitches-on-learning-to-knit/1497d2434f8a_IMG_5755.avif" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>With this, I started off with some stockinette, then increased the number of stitches on the row with the bar increase and three kinds of Make One increase (M1-L, M1-R and M1-O). At that point I did some more stockinette and then some decreases (k2tog, ssk and SKP).</p>
<p>Then there were some yarn overs. It’s unclear to me why yarn overs are taught as a whole separate category or section from increases, since functionally they both are adding stitches. Also at this point in the pattern it seemed like I had fewer stitches on the needle than the pattern or instructions were expecting, but it was time to bind off.</p>
<p>This swatch looks somehow the least ‘nice’ of all of them. I’m not quite sure why. I also struggled quite a lot with tension (i.e.&nbsp;extremely tight stitches to handle), but towards the end I got the end of making it looser. Clearly there’s a balance to be had: tighter makes for neat and tidy, but at a certain point it’s unworkable. Conversely, by the end I was much looser in my hands but that’s where you can see that things look a <em>lot</em> less uniform.</p>
</section>
<section id="next-steps" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-steps">Next steps</h2>
<p>The next (and final) sections in the learning part of the course are weaving in loose ends as well as blocking. I’ll try to block the last swatch to see if that makes things clearer (and just for the experience, not having blocked anything before).</p>
<p>Once that’s all done (tonight, if I’m lucky!), it’ll then be time to put everything I’ve learned into practice by making some larger swatches. These swatches can then be submitted to TKGA for feedback (the <em>correspondence</em> part of correspondence course) which I’m looking forward to.</p>
<p>Down the line, and depending on how the feedback from my first swatches goes, I’d like to maybe try some other courses and perhaps even the <a href="https://tkga.org/certification/master-hand-knitting/">Master Hand Knitting certification</a>. I’ll also be dipping into the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Fearless-Knitting-Workbook-Jennifer-Seiffert/dp/1596681497">Fearless Knitting Workbook</a> which is also swatch-based, a format I’ve been really enjoying as it allows me to get fast feedback and improve my skills.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>crafting</category>
  <category>learning</category>
  <category>crafts</category>
  <category>skills</category>
  <category>lessonslearnt</category>
  <category>knitting</category>
  <guid>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2025-01-05-first-stitches-on-learning-to-knit.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Language Learning Crash Course: from slightly more than zero to slightly less than advanced</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Strick van Linschoten</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2023-08-10-language-study-zero-to-hero.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://alexstrick.com/personal/images/2023-08-10-language-study-zero-to-hero/38b79d97dc3e_strickvl_a_female_turkish_student_studying_languages_in_Munich__661ccaec-73a2-4f72-ae93-8bc9ca8d8b05.avif" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>A colleague at work asked me for some tips on learning German and her situation and goals were fairly common so I thought I’d write up some notes here.</p>
<p>For the specific scenario under consideration, and to ground what follows: my colleague’s mother tongue is not English, but she wants to learn German since she now lives there. She’s interested in all the skills and wants to be able to read complex literature and philosophy, for example, but in the short-term building up spoken abilities is the main focus and intention. She knows a few words / phrases here and there but not too much more than that.</p>
<section id="context-foundations" class="level1">
<h1>🪨 Context / Foundations</h1>
<p>I’ll start with some general context and foundations that I think should form the basis for what follows:</p>
<ul>
<li>If you’re about to invest a bunch of time / effort (and probably money, either in the form of your time or for books/teachers) into learning a language you should make the investment in <strong>a spaced repetition system</strong> like <a href="https://apps.ankiweb.net/">Anki</a>. It’ll repay the effort you put in and is anyway a more efficient way to learn.</li>
<li>Use <strong>focused feedback</strong> of various kinds to improve your ability to do things with your target language. This can take many forms, but it’s a core principle that you should keep returning to. For example, this might mean feedback on pronunciation, or sentences you’re writing, or even words that you’re studying (in the form of active recall with Anki).</li>
<li>Pick <strong>good quality materials</strong> to support your study. For some languages (popular / commonly-spoken languages) these will probably be cheap. For lower-resourced languages these are often eye-waveringly expensive. Bit the bullet. Good materials make a big difference, though it’s worth taking advice from someone who’s studied the same language as to whether a particular book is good or not.</li>
<li><strong>Stay laser focused</strong> in what you do / apply the 80:20 principle. With language learning, especially at the early stages, there’s a fair amount of boilerplate work that just needs to be done (see most of the things in the first ‘True Basics’ section below) and there are strong reasons why you should do those things etc. Basically: stick with these things and don’t deviate too much. (This only applies if you’re trying to be as efficient as possible in your language learning. It’s entirely within reason that you’d <em>not</em> need to be efficient, in which case many options open up!)</li>
<li>Related: <strong>Be clear</strong> about what it means to level up. There are a million and one things that you could do at any single point during your language learning and it helps to be clear about what you’re doing and why, then work on it, complete it and then reflect and move onto the next thing.</li>
<li>Ingest <strong>comprehensible input</strong> where possible. This is a deep topic, but the basic idea here is that you should try as much as possible to read authentic materials that are almost completely within your capacity/level to understand. Ideally they should be interesting materials and you should be motivated to understand their contents. (Note that spoken conversations can be comprehensible input as well!)</li>
</ul>
<p>These are the core foundations that I (with a half-dozen languages under my belt and experience learning bits of quite a few more, plus lots of time spent reading about and trying out language learning methods) believe are at the core of any efforts you should take. If any of the above are unclear, it can be useful to clarify (with me, or with some other source) but don’t get too lost down the (deep) rabbit-hole of methodology as it will detract from your original goal.</p>
<p>All of what follows assumes that you’re serious about your language studies and are willing to invest some time into it. To my mind, this means something like 30-60 minutes every day minimum, six days per week. You’ll see the most progress early on and it can actually help to invest a little more time early on since seeing your fast progress will increase your motivation in turn, but only you know your circumstances and what works.</p>
</section>
<section id="true-basics" class="level1">
<h1>🍼 True Basics</h1>
<p>This is the phase where you start from nothing and no knowledge to where you have learnt some of the most commonly used words and phrases as well as have a good understanding of the pronunciation and basic grammar. Depending on how much time you put in, this phase should take somewhere on the order of 2-5 weeks.</p>
<p>The things you should work your way to accomplish here include:</p>
<ul>
<li>learning some basic spoken phrases that you’ll use frequently (think ‘thank you’, ‘good bye’, ‘how much is …’, counting from 0-100, ‘what does … mean’ and so on). You can get these (and the pronunciation for them) from many places on line or in a basic phrasebook.</li>
<li>learn roughly 600 of the most frequently-used words for your target language. Many languages have something called a ‘frequency dictionary’ (or an equivalent list published online) which orders the words of that language in order of how common those words are. There are different approaches to exactly which list to pick (go with a <a href="https://blog.fluent-forever.com/appendix5/">Gabe Wyner 625 list</a> if it exists (<a href="https://fluent-forever.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/GERMAN-Awesome-Words-demo-pages.pdf">here’s an extract/preview</a> for German), otherwise go with <a href="https://www.routledge.com/Routledge-Frequency-Dictionaries/book-series/RFD">the Routledge frequency lists</a>, otherwise try to find something else!), but basically you are aiming to bootstrap your language abilities. The ‘why’ behind this is that first 500-100 words make up a really high % of the words that you’ll see in any text (80+% depending on the difficulty of the language) so if you invest in those common words earlier you’ll be in a good place to progress forward.</li>
</ul>
<p>You’ll want these materials to end up into Anki so you can continue to be tested on them so you don’t forget them. Here, for example is a card I created for a word that means ‘ripped / torn’ in Arabic.</p>
<p><img src="https://alexstrick.com/personal/images/2023-08-10-language-study-zero-to-hero/485d8e7e64cd_ScreenShot_2023-08-10_at_08.25.04.avif" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>I get shown the picture and then need to come up with the word in Arabic for that concept. Note that I chose a quirky image on purpose.</p>
<ul>
<li>Learn the alphabet: (I’m thinking of languages like Russian / Arabic etc here, and <em>not</em> something like Japanese / Chinese). You’re in this for the long-haul, and most comprehensible input that is efficient for you to ingest is in the form of written texts so you should just bite the bullet and learn the alphabet and how to pronounce it. It’s not that hard! Even an alphabet with a bad reputation like Arabic can be learned in a weekend.</li>
<li>Get a basic understanding of some core grammar. Good phrasebooks will usually have a section where they spend a few pages outlining how the language works with some basic grammar. (i.e.&nbsp;things like ‘verbs always go at the end of sentences’ or ‘nouns take a bunch of different endings depending on the role a word has in the sentence’, and so on.) You’re not trying to master any of this, but you <em>are</em> trying to bootstrap your awareness of some of the core structures of how a language works.</li>
<li>Try to listen to the language being used / spoken. If possible, try to make whatever you’re listening to also something that you can mostly understand. (For some people this might be family or friends conversations, for others this might be other audio materials at a beginner level.) The goal here is to start to get the sound and feel for the rhythms of the language to bury its way into your ear.</li>
</ul>
<section id="how-what-basics" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-what-basics">How / What?: Basics</h2>
<p>There are many (<em>many</em>) options at the total beginner level. My go-to sources / methods are some combination or selection of the following. It’s really hard to give generic advice here so YMMV, but all these are suitable for this level:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.michelthomas.com/learn-german/">Michel Thomas course</a> (if it exists for your language, do all courses / extensions that exist (usually 2 levels plus a vocab extension pack)). These are audio courses that will give you a solid basic foundation. As an alternative or sometimes additional option, you might want to try <a href="https://www.pimsleur.com/learn-german">Pimsleur courses</a> (again, if they exist). These are not cheap, but they’re a good way to get going.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.routledge.com/Routledge-Frequency-Dictionaries/book-series/RFD">Frequency dictionary</a> and/or lists: <a href="https://fluent-forever.com/">Gabe Wyner’s Fluent Forever app</a> is based around the concept of frequency dictionary lists so if it supports your language then you can either use that app or just get the raw word list and create your own flashcards + study those basic words.</li>
<li>Something like a <a href="https://www.duolingo.com/">Duolingo</a> / <a href="https://languagedrops.com/">Drops</a> / <a href="https://www.languagetransfer.org/">Language Transfer</a> course if it exists for your language. These are a double-edge sword since Duolingo by now has quite extensive courses available for popular languages. I wouldn’t recommend using it as your core source of studies because the likelihood is that you’ll drop away from your studies before completing it. That said, they do have mostly solid materials and they have spaced repetition (of some kind) built in so if you’re someone who lives to complete things and can invest a bit of time into moving through the materials quickly, then these kinds of courses aren’t the <em>worst</em> idea. (But definitely see them as a means to the wider end and not the core of what you do.) If you’re someone who where possible prefers to study / learn away from technology / apps, try <a href="https://www.assimil.com/en/articles/5-the-assimil-method">the excellent ‘Assimil’ books</a> / course as the equivalent for this. (Note that this section potentially takes you very far off from the 2-5 weeks estimate I mentioned above. Only you know the extent to which you can afford to really invest in foundations.)</li>
<li>Very easy readers. Again, if your language is popular then you might have access to these kinds of readers. Sometimes they’re developed for children, but other times they’re also available for adult students too. You’re looking for something (it’ll often be advertised as such) with a small / limited vocabulary size of words used. This is on the border with the next phase of study, so this can and will also be part of what you do next.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="invest-in-sentences-and-your-comprehensible-input" class="level1">
<h1>📚 Invest in sentences and your comprehensible input</h1>
<p>At this point, somewhere in the middle of the basic phase and on your way to the next phase, you’ll want to start investing into generating your own sentence-level comprehensible input. One way is to take the 600+ word frequency list and use those words as the basis of making basic sentences. Note that these can and will be really basic. You will likely want to do this in collaboration either with a teacher, or a friend or someone who can correct the things you’re writing / producing. All these sentences and materials should then be fed into your spaced repetition system / Anki. For example, here’s the back of a card where I’m being tested to produce a particular phrase that was missing (where the <code>...</code> is in the sentence).</p>
<p><img src="https://alexstrick.com/personal/images/2023-08-10-language-study-zero-to-hero/51b716cb10db_ScreenShot_2023-08-10_at_08.30.26.avif" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>There’s a picture above it to jog my memory if the sentence doesn’t. And you can’t hear it here, but there’s also audio for the missing word / phrase. You’ll want to be generating a lot of these kind of cards, not only because vocabulary learning <em>in the context of actual sentences / real language</em> is extremely powerful but also because it solidifies the root grammar structures, syntax and common ways of building language in your mind.</p>
</section>
<section id="middle-earth-getting-independent" class="level1">
<h1>🚘 Middle Earth: Getting Independent</h1>
<p>Some people actually stop here. If you’re just going on holiday and you want to be able to be active using the language, understand some basic things and have some simple conversations, you actually don’t need too much more. Everything you do from here on is because you are interested in levelling up and (eventually) reaching greater comprehension of a wider variety and level of materials.</p>
<p>This middle stage is where a lot of people get stuck. It’s important to know that the intermediate plateau is a real thing and you will need strategies to not end up here forever (or quit, which will also eventually happen if you stay here for too long). (I <a href="https://www.languagecoach.io/masterarabic">wrote a whole book</a> about strategies to get out of the intermediate plateau for Arabic, but the first section of the book applies to any other language as well. The book is available for free along with a bunch of audio interviews with language learning experts.)</p>
<p>The specifics of what you do in this middle stage is also heavily dependent on what your interests / motivations are for studying this language. In other words, are you mostly interested in getting really good at spoken conversations + listening, or do you actually not care about spoken language at all and mainly want to be able to read authentic materials without ever needing to to speak to anyone?</p>
<p>Core parts of this stage:</p>
<ul>
<li>continuing down the road of the frequency dictionary. Probably at the end of this stage you want to have mastered at least the 2000 most frequently used words, but ideally you’d get through most of the top 5000 most frequently used words. There are lots of ways that you can accomplish this, and it shouldn’t just be a case of you rote memorising the words. Everything you do in this phase should be intertwined with comprehensible input of some kind, and vocabulary should always be learned within the context of authentic language but there are lots of ways of doing that so you’ll have to figure out what applies best for your situation and needs.</li>
<li>collocations / context: at this stage you want to be maximising your input to the core structures and ways your target language is used. Most words don’t exist in a vacuum, and the further you get down the frequency list (or the more advanced your language source materials get) the more small bits of context and shifts in how individual words are used will make more difference. All of this is just me repeating that you should be reading and exposing yourself to lots of pieces of language.</li>
<li>skill-dependent exercises and approaches: this is unfortunately vague, but depending on your interests and motivation you’ll want to do one thing or another. For speaking, to give some examples, usually what I recommend is that you tackle a series of ‘islands’ that are defined by your interests. This means starting with a situation or a kind of conversation that you know you want to be really comfortable having. Perhaps you want to be able to talk about your daily routine, or maybe you want to be able to talk about food and the things you eat or cook. Then there are a series of things you’d do to prepare for mastering this ‘island’: gathering relevant vocabulary, thinking through the kinds of questions and/or answers that would come up during the conversation, generating some possible options or prepared answers or questions, practicing those with yourself and then later others, and so on. But really there are a million different ways to slice this depending on your interests and specific circumstances.</li>
</ul>
<section id="how-what" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-what">How / What?</h2>
<p>What does this mean in specific? Some variation or combination of the following would be common:</p>
<ul>
<li>reading a lot in graded readers (hopefully these exist for your target language)</li>
<li>graded listening: again, these hopefully exist for your language</li>
<li>italki lessons or targeted spoken practice with a teacher (depending on what specific approaches you take)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.clozemaster.com/">Clozemaster</a> or <a href="https://ai.glossika.com/">Glossika</a>: these are two tools that allow you to work your way through the most frequently used words using spaced repetition and context-rich language selections. Both also offer some kind of audio component. You might not need this if you have a solid method / rhythm already going with your use of Anki, but it’s worth trying out at least to see if it clicks.</li>
<li>writing sentences / paragraphs, then having them corrected, and then using the corrected versions of the language in Anki along with cloze deletion (a variation of what I showed above with the sentence and then a word or phrase missing that you have to guess) to practice the language used in a particular sentence.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="onwards-independent-study-land" class="level1">
<h1>😎 Onwards: Independent Study Land</h1>
<p>At this point in your journey, you’re at the B2 level and maybe soon to be C1. Your goal and process at this point is independent study: you’re choosing materials and areas motivated by your interests. If you’re still going + studying and you reached this level, the process never ends from here on out. It’s just an ongoing set of little deep-dives into lots of different areas depending on your needs and interests.</p>
<p>Everything at this level is dependent on the skills you’re working on, and your needs in terms of vocabulary / topic areas. Your vocabulary goals will be to move from the 5000 most frequent words on out into the next 5000-10,000 words after that, but usually it doesn’t make sense to look at a literal frequency list for the words beyond 5000. For starters, they often don’t exist, and your ‘next words’ will differ from person to person. You’ll likely have a bunch of sub-areas that you get good at beyond the core 5000. For example, for me, I got really good at medical vocabulary (cardiology + neurology) in Dutch but I’m much weaker in other areas. The specific areas you spend time on will be driven by your needs and interests.</p>
<section id="how-what-1" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-what-1">How / What?</h2>
<p>Almost everything here is driven by specific needs, but it will involve and include:</p>
<ul>
<li>lots of learner-driven comprehensible input</li>
<li>needs-driven activities (whether you’re still focused on spoken prowess vs reading vs listening vs writing)</li>
<li>open-ended practice like the kinds of tasks recommended by <a href="https://www.languagecoach.io/coachbot">my (free) CoachBot self-study tool</a>.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="going-deeper" class="level1">
<h1>Going deeper</h1>
<p>Most of what I wrote above was some concrete thoughts on paper that would serve as the basis for a conversation and I’m fully aware that lots of details were buried within or barely mentioned. Usually what I’d do after sketching out this overview is drill down into your individual situation and start to sketch out a more specific / precise plan, but this is a blog and I don’t do coaching professionally any more!</p>
<p>Nevertheless, it’s useful to be aware of the bigger picture and I hope that this blog served as a highly general overview that can drive further exploration and experiments in your own language-learning journey!</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>language</category>
  <category>study</category>
  <category>learning</category>
  <category>education</category>
  <category>languages</category>
  <category>languagecoaching</category>
  <guid>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2023-08-10-language-study-zero-to-hero.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>All the things I wish I knew about studying at school</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Strick van Linschoten</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2023-08-06-all-the-things-i-wish-i-knew-about-studying-at-school.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://alexstrick.com/personal/images/2023-08-06-all-the-things-i-wish-i-knew-about-studying-at-school/ec3946e22039_strickvl_study_skills_85e9b059-dc1b-49d1-99a9-c8edce64dc76.avif" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>My niece reached out to me a few days back asking about tips for studying at school. She was specifically interested in any ideas I had about how to excel in her maths studies. I wrote up my thoughts for her and it occurred to me yesterday that there might be some benefit from putting these notes online as well.</p>
<p>Without further ado, therefore…</p>
<section id="study-skills-advice" class="level1">
<h1>Study Skills Advice</h1>
<p>As I understand it, your question takes two parts:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>how do I learn / study better</li>
<li>how do I specifically learn / study for my upcoming exams (in particular for mathematics)</li>
</ol>
<p>I’ve split my response up into two parts since they’re somehow related but also different. Part one (‘how do I learn new things’) is sort of required for part two (‘what do I have to do to get good grades on my exams’), since it’s pretty hard to try to cram ideas and concepts into your head if you don’t first understand them.</p>
<section id="learning-to-understand" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="learning-to-understand">1. Learning to Understand</h2>
<section id="something-you-just-have-to-learn" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="something-you-just-have-to-learn">Something you just have to ‘learn’</h3>
<p>First off, you’ll want to learn the small tiny ‘fact-like’ things first. Some of this you just have to put in some work and learn them. It’ll help you a LOT when it comes to getting a grasp on the bigger-picture concepts. To give an example, if there are certain equations or definitions of concepts, it can help to take a bit of time and just learn those by heart (in whatever way usually works for you for that). Note that this is limited to just small fact-like things. For sciences, maybe there are some facts or properties of something derived from the periodic table, etc, that are important. In the specific case of quadratics that you asked about, it might be simple things like:</p>
<ul>
<li>the usual form of a quadratic equation</li>
<li>the quadratic formula</li>
<li>‘what is a discriminant’</li>
<li>what does the completed square form look like, and how do you solve it?</li>
<li>what does this or that quadratic look like when you graph it out?</li>
</ul>
<p>The key thing is to isolated and master those tiny morsels of information / facts early on, since a) it needs to be done anyway and b) it’ll help you with the big-picture stuff. Sometimes textbooks help out by highlighting or bolding those key concepts. Just make sure you’re not just trying to learn EVERYTHING by rote, since that advice is as good as no advice in my opinion!</p>
</section>
<section id="learning-for-understanding-foundations" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="learning-for-understanding-foundations">Learning for understanding: foundations</h3>
<p>Something else I’ll say early on is that there are some core foundations that will serve you well:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>start with a / the problem</strong> — it will help to try to wrestle with the kinds of things you’re expected to do with this particular topic you’re studying. It can actually help you to do this at the very beginning of starting a new topic: before you even study things, take a look at the kinds of questions that you’ll be tested on and expected to answer. Maybe even try to solve them. You’ll learn a lot about the subject area just by rolling around in the mud and struggling a bit.</li>
<li><strong>curiosity</strong> — this almost goes without saying, but you should try to find a way to be curious about whatever you’re meant to be studying. It’ll help a LOT with your motivation and interest, which will in turn help you keep moving forward and give you energy at moments when things get hard. Sometimes the trick to this is just trying to ask questions about whatever it is you’re studying: why is this important? how does it connect to topic X or Y we already studied? what is most surprising about this topic? Sometimes it can also help to know a tiny bit about the history of a topic. Calculus is a bit down the road in terms of your studies, but back in the day (late 19th century, early 20th century) there were really epic debates between the various people who were developing this new area of maths. Lots of drama and falling out between people. So sometimes just knowing a bit about the personalities behind things can help.</li>
<li><strong>growth mindset</strong> — I <a href="https://www.alexstrick.com/blog/2016/10/skills-development-foundations">wrote a blog</a> on this a while back but the core thing is just to <em>believe that you have it in you to master this thing</em>. Once you have that, and if you start from that place, then you’ll have much of what you need to keep moving forward. And as one teacher once told me, as long as you never give up then you’ll eventually master it. Sometimes you just have to be a bit patient. Most things come if you give them enough time :)</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="retrieval-practice" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="retrieval-practice">Retrieval Practice</h3>
<p>This is sort of the core of most learning, in my opinion, and I have a lot of thoughts and practice around this. (Have read a LOT about what research recommends in this area, but I figure you’re interested mostly in whatever is practical so I’ll keep it mostly at that level.)</p>
<p>The core: if you want to learn something / master it, you have to retrieve it from your memory somehow. (Retrieve can mean lost of things: for German vocabulary it might mean knowing the gender or translation of a particular word. For Maths it might mean a particular formula, or even a high level understanding of how one concept relates to another.)</p>
<p>The important thing about this retrieval is that it will be and should be hard to do. (This is one reason why people don’t necessarily enjoy doing this, and even fewer actually do it.) It’s hard to struggle to put together a coherent explanation of topic x or y, but that struggle is what helps create neural pathways that cement the understanding going forward.</p>
<p>One possible way you could do this is to write short summaries of what you understood of a particular topic, then check your notes to see if you were correct. IMPORTANT: the key thing is to do this from memory / without notes. Otherwise you’re not actually reinforcing materials in your head.</p>
<p>Another way of testing things (e.g.&nbsp;in your specific case of quadratics) is to do practice examples. Your school or textbook probably gives you some practice examples, but you shouldn’t confine yourself just to doing those. Make up your own examples, or go online and find more examples (use Khan Academy or whatever).</p>
<p>It can also help to make <em>distilled summary sheets</em> at some point during your studies which gather together your understanding on a single piece of paper for the entire topic. Here actually you can see the one I made digitally for my own study of quadratics a few months ago:</p>
<p><img src="https://alexstrick.com/personal/images/2023-08-06-all-the-things-i-wish-i-knew-about-studying-at-school/85f6860731ec_ScreenShot_2023-08-06_at_20.47.47.avif" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The key thing with retrieval practice is to get a lot of it, and to try to make it the ‘hard’ / ‘difficult’ kind of retrieval. Mostly this starts with a blank sheet of paper and then you try to write down what you know about a topic, or a concept, or whatever specific thing you’re trying to understand. Writing things down will help you realise (quickly! painfully!) which parts you don’t <em>actually</em> understand. So it’s as much to reveal to you which parts you need to work on as it is for anything else.</p>
<p>(There’s <a href="https://collegeinfogeek.com/feynman-technique/">a much-praised technique</a> named after a well-known American scientist, Richard Feynman, and you can do something like this, too:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Write the title of a topic that you want to study / test yourself on</li>
<li>Write or map out an explanation of that subject intelligible / appropriate to a non-specialist. Do this from memory.</li>
<li>Identify any gaps in your explanation / understanding.</li>
<li>Relearn / restudy / interrogate to fill in the gaps.</li>
</ol>
<p>You can use narrative / diagrams to condense and clarify your explanation. It’s basically the same idea. And yes, bullet points or spider diagrams are all possible ways of doing this.)</p>
</section>
<section id="developing-mental-models" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="developing-mental-models">Developing mental models</h3>
<p>There’s this idea that the whole thing you’re doing when you learn something is developing ‘mental models’, which I personally find a bit hard to wrap my head around, but it is a thing… It’s maybe the next layer up in what’s happening when you try to learn something.</p>
<p>Mental models are, for me, about making a topic your own somehow. They’re also about making the concepts of that topic manipulable somehow.</p>
<p>The ‘making it your own’ part has a lot to do with confidence, somehow, but it’s also just feeling familiar and effective with the concepts that you feel comfortable solving problems in that area. If you see a problem, e.g., you know which techniques (or which subset of techniques) are needed to solve it. If there are multiple possible ways to solve something, you’ll have a good feel for the tradeoffs: i.e.&nbsp;why this way is better than that way etc. In the case of quadratics, for example, we know that there is this amazing thing which is the quadratic formula, but you probably don’t want to use that formula the whole time because it’s easy to make a mistake with it and it’s a bit cumbersome. Instead, we often use other simpler techniques that work for many (if not totally 100%) of the problems that you’ll be exposed to.</p>
<p>One way to help develop mental models is to try to explain the topic to someone else. You already did a bit of this in the retrieval practice above: trying to explain it on paper is already some of this. But trying to explain a topic to people at different levels of understanding can be really clarifying. I.e. if you had to explain quadratics to a 5-year old it’s probably different to how you’d explain it to a 40-year old. (Along with this, you can test out this approach by chatting with a chatbot about the topic. I’m sure you’ve heard of ChatGPT, but <a href="https://poe.com/Claude-instant">Claude</a> is also another good option, esp for things like maths. The key thing is to start the conversation by saying something like “I would like to have a conversation about quadratics. I’ve been studying it and I’d like to test out my explanations of some core concepts with you. I would like you to tell me if things feel unclear about what I’m saying, or if you notice that there are some areas where I could improve my understanding.”)</p>
<p>(While we’re here, using things like ChatGPT to develop mental models can be useful. I will often have conversations that begin with something like “What is a good way to think about the discriminant in relation to quadratic equations? Please make your explanation simple to follow and use some concrete items in your reply, like only items that you’d find in a kitchen.”)</p>
<p>Making mental models is hard! But the work you do to solidify things and make them your own is really worth it!</p>
<p>Anyway, the big point here is to reflect on what you’re studying. Make sure to also give some time to connecting it to other things either in your maths studies or outside, or even life in general. It’s not the best to just view everything completely isolated and disconnected from the other topics, so try to take a step back from time to time! (Unfortunately, most schools aren’t built to encourage that process much, but it’s important!)</p>
</section>
<section id="specific-contexts" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="specific-contexts">Specific contexts</h3>
<p>There are some other specific contexts that require different / more targeted advice, but you didn’t mention them so I’ll ignore them a bit. But language learning is one of them, and learning some kind of ‘motor skill’ is another (i.e.&nbsp;that requires coordination or physical movement like playing golf or the yoyo or whatever).</p>
</section>
<section id="in-practice-understanding-quadratics" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="in-practice-understanding-quadratics">In Practice: Understanding Quadratics</h3>
<p>To summarise the practical points listed above:</p>
<ul>
<li>learn the small fact-sized pieces early on</li>
<li>get lots of retrieval practice (a mixture of examples of doing whatever the skill requires of you, and/or writing or explaining the topic at various levels)</li>
<li>develop mental models where you can.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="studying-for-exams" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="studying-for-exams">2. Studying for Exams</h2>
<p>I’ll take it for granted that you agree that you can’t study for something without properly understanding it, so somehow the things in part 1 are sort of a prerequisite for this section; you can’t get ready for an exam if you don’t understand what’s going on.</p>
<p>That said, there are some tactical things you can do to help your chances of success once you <em>do</em> have an understanding of a particular topic. Note that for all of this, it’s a bit of a question of picking which parts seem doable / manageable. It’s probably unwise / counterproductive to necessarily try to do EVERYTHING :)</p>
<section id="ground-rules" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ground-rules">Ground rules</h3>
<p>You should understand the requirements of the exam. Take a bit of time to read through some previous exam papers. I’m sure your teachers have also given you clear guidelines on what kinds of things to expect. That will give you a map for how to prepare, so be sure to do this.</p>
</section>
<section id="foundations-exam-study" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="foundations-exam-study">Foundations: Exam Study</h3>
<p>There are some basic foundations here which for various reasons get forgotten when you’re under exam pressure, but it’s good to remind yourself of these, since if you neglect these it’ll negatively affect your ability to study etc.</p>
<ul>
<li>sleep</li>
<li>eating things that nourish your body instead of just feeding cravings</li>
<li>taking breaks (every hour, ideally, get up and walk around for a minute or two)</li>
<li>minimise distractions (put your phone in airplane mode or in a lock box while studying)</li>
<li>movement in general / going out of the house for walks a few times a day is a good minimum.</li>
<li>‘managing your energy’ — this one’s a bit hard to quantify / explain, but I’d say it’s worth trying to embody the principle that you should only study as much today as allows you to keep studying tomorrow. I.e. if you overdo it and you study a lot today, but it’s a bit too much and tomorrow then you can’t do any study etc, then that was counterproductive. (Hope that was clear!)</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="mnemonic-memory-tricks" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mnemonic-memory-tricks">Mnemonic / memory tricks</h3>
<p>There are a TON of memory tricks out in the world. All of them are useful, but not all of them are equally useful for every situation :)</p>
<p>Things like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mnemonic_major_system">the major system</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mnemonic_link_system">the link system</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mnemonic_peg_system">the peg system</a> are all useful, but they require a bit of time and probably also someone who knows how they work to explain them to you.</p>
<p>If you already have a bit of experience with these things, then I’d encourage you to use them in your studies, but if you don’t have much experience then I’d say probably that it’s not going to be the difference between an A and a B grade so probably it’s a waste of your time to try to get into that in the run-up to exams.</p>
<p>That said, it would TOTALLY be a really useful investment to learn a few of these during summer holidays in a non-stress / fun way. You can play around with learning the order of decks of cards etc — I can explain all this if you’re interested — and then you’ll have that skill available to you if you need it next year or throughout your life.</p>
<p>There are some general memory principles that you can rely on in general terms:</p>
<ul>
<li>when trying to remember something, make it memorable in your mind! so maybe try to imagine the concepts as characters in some kind of image in your mind, and use all your senses and bring in some shock or drama etc etc. (LMK if you want more of these kinds of advice. I have a lot, but not sure how useful it is for you right now.)</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="spaced-repetition" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="spaced-repetition">Spaced Repetition</h3>
<p>This is a really useful tool, but it requires a bit of upfront (time) investment and unless you’re feeling super comfortable / not stressed at all, I might suggest to add it to the list of ‘things to learn about over summer / winter (?) holidays’.</p>
<p>Basically this means testing yourself with (digital) flashcards, but the twist is that you only get shown the flashcard at exactly the optimum time / day when you need to be tested on it. (There’s a whole science to this which I won’t go into, but there’s a TON of backing to the fact that this is the way to make things get into your memory.)</p>
<p>The best option for this is a piece of software called <a href="https://apps.ankiweb.net">Anki</a>. It runs on your laptop and phone etc, but it has a bit of a steep learning curve mainly because the defaults it comes with aren’t great. So if you were interested I could help you set that up, but the key thing to know is that using this requires a bit of extra work.</p>
<p>The main idea is that you create (digital) flashcards for all the things you need to know, and then every day you check in with Anki to review whatever cards it says you need to know. There’s an algorithm that calculates which cards you should review. It should mesh well with your intuitive sense of how memory works: i.e.&nbsp;over time you slowly forget things, so Anki will prompt you to recall a particular concept just at the point before you forget it, since that exact moment is the best time to review it. When you review it at that moment and you get it right, it’ll really strengthen your memory for that thing. If you don’t remember it, then it’ll reset the status of that card and it’ll know to show it more often for a few days etc.</p>
<p>There are more manual ways to get the same effect, but (for a lot of reasons) they’re not as effective since humans don’t work / behave like computers so really using a digital tool is the only way to go.</p>
<p>For quadratics, to use my experience, I have a bunch of cards relating to that that I get tested on. Writing a ‘good flashcard’ is a bit of an art, and we can get into that if you’re interested, but I’ll just lay it here as an option for now.</p>
</section>
<section id="interleaving" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="interleaving">Interleaving</h3>
<p>This is a fancy word for saying: ‘don’t study just one topic on its own’. When you’re testing yourself on things that you’ll need to know for exams, make sure to switch things up a lot. This means doing one problem from quadratics, then another relating to trigonometry, and another relating to topic z etc etc.</p>
<p>There is again quite a bit of evidence that this makes you much stronger in your understanding / learning, even though (or maybe because!) it’s a bit harder to do.</p>
<p>If at least part of your review of topics / facts are handled by Anki it’ll take care of giving you random flashcards anyway, so this more relates to things like solving maths problems by hand.</p>
<p>So don’t just do 50 iterations of the same maths problem, in other words. Make sure you’re switching topics etc.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="next-steps" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-steps">3. Next Steps</h2>
<ul>
<li>Check the practical suggestions above</li>
<li>let me know if anything’s unclear / or you want to know more about how to do thing x or y</li>
<li>gather some problems to solve so you can make sure you’re practicing the things you need to study</li>
<li>get into some good habits around retrieval practice (i.e.&nbsp;writing things down to test whether you know them or not)</li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>productivity</category>
  <category>memory</category>
  <category>study</category>
  <category>skills</category>
  <category>mathematics</category>
  <category>memorisation</category>
  <category>education</category>
  <guid>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2023-08-06-all-the-things-i-wish-i-knew-about-studying-at-school.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Automating social media posting for my new blogposts</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Strick van Linschoten</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2023-07-15-automating-social-media-posting.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I love blogging and I’ve benefitted a lot from what it’s done for me ever since I started my first Geocities page in the mid 1990s. I maintain a technical blog at mlops.systems and a somewhat less technical blog at alexstrick.com/blog, though hope at some point to merge these together.</p>
<p>In the past I would have been content with ensuring that my blog published an RSS feed and known that anyone wanting to follow what I was writing could do so simply by connecting their feed reader and subscribing. I’ve become more conscious in recent years of a healthy brew of ambivalence, ignorance or even outright hostility to even the idea of RSS feeds and readers. It seems many people don’t have RSS as an essential part of their informational hygiene any more. (I’ll put my sadness / confusion about this to one side for now.)</p>
<p>And if I love blogging, I really dislike having to post my new blog posts to social media one by one, coming up with some catchy yet not overtly breathless summary of what I wrote, since this is apparently what many people use instead of RSS.</p>
<p>I’ve been grumbling under my breath about this situation for this for a few years now, but when ChatGPT came out it seemed like an obvious use: summarise my blogpost and repost to all my social media accounts taking into account their particular needs. (Mastodon uses hashtags more than the others, whereas LinkedIn posts can be a bit longer, vs Twitter which needs to be a bit shorter and so on.)</p>
<p>I held off, thinking I’d want to set up some system fully under my control involving serverless function calls and so on, but then I was reminded that I already use <a href="https://zapier.com/">Zapier</a> for some other administrative tasks. So this afternoon I set up and turned on some automation for social media posting to my Mastodon, Twitter and LinkedIn accounts. Posting happens at one step removed since I queue my posts in <a href="https://buffer.com">Buffer</a> so that they go out at a time when people are more likely to see them. I apologise / don’t apologise for this. My blog writings remain wholly un-automated; it would completely remove the point of ‘learning through writing’ if I were to automate the things that I blog about. My social media postings (just one post per blogpost so as not to spam you all) are from now on automated. As an additional courtesy / discourtesy, I’ve tweaked the prompt such that the social media posts should always read just slightly ‘off’ and will be labelled with an <code>#automated</code> hashtag.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>productivity</category>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>useful-tools</category>
  <category>automation</category>
  <category>social-media</category>
  <category>technology</category>
  <guid>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2023-07-15-automating-social-media-posting.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jul 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Vermeer at the Rijksmuseum</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Strick van Linschoten</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2023-02-19-vermeer-at-the-rijksmuseum.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>[caption id=“” align=“alignnone” width=“768”]<img src="https://alexstrick.com/personal/images/2023-02-19-vermeer-at-the-rijksmuseum/9f43da265fac_vermeer-sd.avif" class="img-fluid" alt="Not by Vermeer. This generated by my friend Stable Diffusion."> Not by Vermeer. This generated by my friend Stable Diffusion. [/caption]</p>
<p>I visited <a href="https://www.rijksmuseum.nl/en/whats-on/exhibitions/vermeer">the bumper Vermeer exhibition</a> today in Amsterdam. I had previously seen many of the works separately in different galleries in the USA and here in the Netherlands, but there’s certainly a raw power to bringing them all together in the same space.</p>
<p>Above all, it was the still city landscapes from Delft that left the biggest impression. These small scenes captured so much and seemed to pull you in as if weighted down from within.</p>
<p>I’m glad I managed to get tickets to the exhibition, but will enjoy revisiting the two Delft paintings when they return to the Hague later in the year.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>art</category>
  <category>reviews</category>
  <category>netherlands</category>
  <guid>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2023-02-19-vermeer-at-the-rijksmuseum.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 18 Feb 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2022 Readings</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Strick van Linschoten</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2022-12-27-2022-readings.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I read 75 books this year (over 22,000 pages), and a few days still remain. Looking back over the full list, I’m both surprised at how many were only of middling reward. I think the key is to take one’s sweet time on the true gems and speed through the should-have-been-a-blog-post dross. Out of the gems, the following stand out:</p>
<ul>
<li>Sabine Hossenfelder’s <em>Lost in Math: How Beauty Leads Physics Astray</em>. We’re told so often about how mathematics and physics is beautiful, how it <em>makes sense</em> and that finding those kinds of beauty-centric explanations is what we should be aiming for, so I was surprised and invigorated by a book about how the opposite might well be the case. It’s a few years old and I’m sure it’s part of a wider argument and debate in the field, but without knowing much more it certainly opened my mind.</li>
<li>Emmanuel Ameisen’s <em>Building Machine Learning Powered Applications: Going from Idea to Product</em> was one of the first things I read as I transitioned into a new field and I often return to it. Lots of hard-won wisdom about the ‘whole game’ of machine learning in the real world, and a story economically-told.</li>
<li>I didn’t read as much science fiction as I’d planned this year, but of the ones that I did, Samuel R. Delany’s <em>Babel-17</em> blew my mind. It’s a classic for a reason, but still amazing to think that it was first published in 1966!</li>
<li>For strong emotions and characters that keep you rooting for them, look no further than Shobha Rao’s <em>Girls Burn Brighter</em>. Not a light read by any means, but a strong showing from start to finish.</li>
<li>I devoured the eight currently-available parts of Martha Wells’ <em>Murderbot Diaries</em> over the course of a few weeks. They’re all fast-paced and once you’ve read the first the general conceit of the series wears off, but the character is so incredibly enjoyable. Come for the smart science fiction, stay for the strong character development. Definitely my favourite find of the year.</li>
<li>Kate Crawford’s <em>Atlas of AI: Power, Politics and the Planetary Costs of Artificial Intelligence</em> was a recommendation from a friend and it was a sharply sobering read in a discipline where ML boosterism is all too common. Nothing in there was particularly news, per se, but the picture as a whole raised important questions. Moreover, the balance between fine-grained detail and the big-picture worked well in this book.</li>
<li>I reread Chanel Miller’s <em>Know My Name</em> this year. Still as devastating and powerful as when I first read it, and a searing indictment of the criminal process for cases of sexual assault in the United Status. Required reading.</li>
<li>Dostoevsky’s <em>Crime and Punishment</em>, a late entry this year, was my first Dostoevsky and I’m still thinking about quite a few of the scenes, weeks after putting the book down. In particular, the last time Raskolnikov meets with his mother.</li>
<li>Some books are unexpected gifts, like Sarah Polley’s collection of stories-almost-not-told entitled <em>Run Towards the Danger: Confrontations with a Body of Memory</em>. Each essay is unexpected, brave and deftly constructed. I’ve watched most of what she’s been involved in since <em>The Sweet Hereafter</em> and this book certainly didn’t disappoint.</li>
<li>Finally, I read through the two books written by David Goggins, <em>Can’t Hurt Me</em> and <em>Never Finished</em> and something about his take on suffering and the lessons it has to teach resonates a lot with me. I’ll be returning to these to sort through his experience at a later date.</li>
</ul>



 ]]></description>
  <category>books</category>
  <category>reading</category>
  <guid>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2022-12-27-2022-readings.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 26 Dec 2022 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>On the interpretability of models</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Strick van Linschoten</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2021-05-28-on-the-interpretability-of-models.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>A <a href="https://www.brightworkresearch.com/the-problematic-black-box-nature-of-neural-networks-and-deep-learning/">common</a> <a href="https://www.datanami.com/2017/10/27/dealing-deep-learnings-big-black-box-problem/">criticism</a> of deep learning models is that they are ‘black boxes’. You put data in one end as your inputs, the argument goes, and you get some predictions or results out the other end, but you have no idea <em>why</em> the model gave your those predictions.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://external-content.duckduckgo.com/iu/?u=https%3A%2F%2Fi0.wp.com%2Fwww.skampakis.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2018%2F03%2FDeep-Neural-Network-What-is-Deep-Learning-Edureka.png&amp;f=1&amp;nofb=1" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Ways of interpreting learning in computer vision models - credit https://thedatascientist.com/what-deep-learning-is-and-isnt/</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This has something to do with how neural networks work: you often have many layers that are busy with the ‘learning’, and each successive layer may be able to interpret or recognise more features or greater levels of abstraction. In the above image, you can get a sense of how the earlier layers (on the left) are learning basic contour features and then these get abstracted together in more general face features and so on.</p>
<p>Some of this also has to do with the fact that when you train your model, you do so assuming that the model will be used on data that the model hasn’t seen. In this (common) use case, it becomes a bit harder to say exactly why a certain prediction was made, though there are a lot of ways we can start to open up the black box.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>science</category>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>deep-learning</category>
  <category>data</category>
  <category>technology</category>
  <category>deeplearning</category>
  <guid>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2021-05-28-on-the-interpretability-of-models.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 27 May 2021 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>FastAI Lesson Zero: video notes</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Strick van Linschoten</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2021-05-27-fastai-lesson-zero.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>[These are mainly notes for myself, based off Jeremy Howard’s ‘Lesson 0’ <a href="https://youtu.be/gGxe2mN3kAg">video</a> that was recently posted. It doesn’t capture the entirety of what was said during the course, but it includes pieces that I felt are relevant to me now and that might be relevant to me in the future.]</p>
<ul>
<li>decide when you’re studying
<ul>
<li>be precise about how much time you’re going to spend</li>
<li>think about how it’s going to fit into your day or your life</li>
<li>give yourself deadlines and goals, perhaps, but also don’t worry if disruptions happen.</li>
<li>Mainly make sure that if something <em>does</em> come up, make sure you get back on the horse and keep going. (Tenacity counts for a lot)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Finish. The. Course.
<ul>
<li>make a commitment to complete <a href="https://course.fast.ai">the course</a>, and make sure you actually do that.</li>
<li>If you’re attending the course and working through it, you should follow through on your original commitment and actually work through the course.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Finish a Project
<ul>
<li>build a project and make it really great.</li>
<li>You’ll probably have several projects here and there that you work on during the course of the fastai course, but at a minimum make sure you pick one of those and make it really great.</li>
<li>(It doesn’t have to be unique or world-changing. Even replicating something that’s already in existence can still be worth it).</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Find good role models
<ul>
<li>Jeremy raises up the example of <a href="https://twitter.com/radekosmulski/">Radek Osmulski</a> (who recently published an ebook called <a href="https://gumroad.com/l/learn_deep_learning">Meta Learning</a>).</li>
<li>(<a href="https://twitter.com/jeremyphoward/">Jeremy</a> himself is a good role model too).</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Learn by doing. Use what you learn and figure out the rest as you go. (Don’t get paralyzed by trying to learn ‘pre-requisites’ like complex mathematics topics, esp since most of them aren’t actually needed to become a practitioner).</li>
<li>Share and communicate your work
<ul>
<li>(Jeremy doesn’t mention the book, but I’ll insert here that the book “<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Show-Your-Work-Austin-Kleon/dp/076117897X/ref=tmm_pap_swatch_0?qid=1621525599&amp;sr=1-1&amp;tag=soumet-20&amp;_encoding=UTF8">Show Your Work</a>” by Austin Kleon is a great starter on this point).</li>
<li>If you consistently blog during your studies, at the end of it you’ll likely have a huge collection of artefacts of that study, showing what you’ve learned and accomplished.</li>
<li>Alongside that, being a good citizen and contributing in the forums etc is also a really solid way to extend whatever knowledge you have to others, and quite possibly cement things in your own mind as you reply.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>How to do a lesson
<ul>
<li>watch the video / read the chapter</li>
<li>Run the notebook &amp; experiment — play around with things + make sure you actually understand what’s happening</li>
<li>Reproduce the notebook from scratch — (and really start with nothing here, and try to reimplement whatever was done during the lesson. From previous experience, this work will be hard, but it’s super worth it. Recall learning is the best kind of learning)</li>
<li>Repeat with a different dataset — use the techniques you learned in the course on a dataset of your own / or solve some related problem using these techniques</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Using a notebook server vs a full linux server
<ul>
<li>the notebook server allows you to get going much faster</li>
<li>A full linux server is more ‘your own’ and you get to also practice a bunch of other not-specifically-deep-learning skills along the way</li>
<li>With the <a href="https://github.com/fastai/fastsetup">fastsetup</a> library, Jeremy has made getting going with an EC2 instance pretty easy.</li>
<li>the video spends a fair amount of time showing how to do this with Colab Noteboks and a AWS EC2 instance. Refer to the FastAI website and the full video for more details.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Get better as a developer
<ul>
<li>just doing the course, you’ll also work on your development skills along the way</li>
<li>Two important things to do to help with this:
<ul>
<li>Read a lot of code</li>
<li>Write a lot of code</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Start with a simple baseline &amp; get a basic end-to-end solution up and running
<ul>
<li>When you’re working on a project, it’s a really good idea to start with a naive / super-basic baseline so that you know whether you’re making progress or whether you’re achieving anything with the work you’re doing.</li>
<li>Successful ML projects that Jeremy has seen start with the simplest possible end-to-end solution and then incrementally grow from there.</li>
<li>The work of getting your pipeline working / your data imported etc will take a bit of time, and if you get that all sorted upfront it’ll help you focus on the actual work you want to be focused on.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>(At some point during the course) join a <a href="https://www.kaggle.com">Kaggle</a> competition and make a serious attempt to do your best
<ul>
<li>just getting a model on the leaderboard tests your knowledge and your skills</li>
<li>just work regularly on things, show up every day, try to make your model a little better each day</li>
<li>Do these things:</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/radekosmulski/status/1334490647986905089"><img src="https://alexstrick.com/personal/images/2021-05-27-fastai-lesson-zero/ff44b78fb0ed_ScreenShot_2021-05-27_at_12.40.27.avif" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<ul>
<li>For getting a job in the space
<ul>
<li>having a public-facing portfolio of writings and projects will take you a really long way</li>
<li>Some companies are more interested in people having the right credentials etc and will never choose you.</li>
<li>Startups are a great place where this matters less.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Try to take the <a href="https://course19.fast.ai/part2">second course</a>
<ul>
<li>The first course gets you going as a practitioner of deep learning, but the second course allows you to implement algorithms and models from scratch and digs far more into the depths of the subject.</li>
<li>Jeremy wishes more people would take part two + encourages them to do so.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>The <a href="https://github.com/fastai/fastsetup"><code>fastsetup</code></a> library is great for installing everything on a Ubuntu machine (like an AWS EC2 instance)</li>
<li>Experiment tracking software
<ul>
<li>The two big players are <a href="https://www.tensorflow.org/tensorboard/">TensorBoard</a> and <a href="https://wandb.ai/">Weights &amp; Biases</a>.</li>
<li>Jeremy doesn’t use these. Finds it too tempting to spend your time watching your models train instead of doing something else that is probably more valuable.</li>
<li>There are some cases where it might help to use this software.</li>
<li><a href="https://wandb.ai/">Weights &amp; Biases</a> seems like a good company to work for &amp; they’ve hired FastAI grads in the past.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>



 ]]></description>
  <category>productivity</category>
  <category>deep-learning</category>
  <category>study</category>
  <category>fastai</category>
  <category>deeplearning</category>
  <guid>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2021-05-27-fastai-lesson-zero.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2021 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Getting Out of the Intermediate Language Plateau: Arabic Edition / Principles</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Strick van Linschoten</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2021-05-26-arabic-language-plateau-principles.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>[This is part of a series on getting out of a language-learning plateau at the intermediate-advanced level. Check out the other parts here.]</em></p>
<p><img src="https://alexstrick.com/personal/images/2021-05-26-arabic-language-plateau-principles/5ca5bbf280bf_image-asset.avif" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Seasoned language learners are familiar with the concept of the ‘language plateau’. If you’re learning a second language for the first time, you will inevitably reach a point in your studies where your progress seems to flatten. You will find this place and period extremely frustrating.</p>
<p>When you are in your plateau, it’s <a href="http://www.lingholic.com/reaching-a-plateau-in-language-learning-how-to-get-out-of-it/">hard to improve</a> because you’re already at a point of (some kind of) self-sufficiency. You can express yourself. You understand most of what is going on in a conversation or TV series you watch. You can write things and people will understand what you’re saying. You could (and many do) stop your studies at this point and still be ‘functional’ in the language.</p>
<p>Getting out of this flat, dead zone is what I want to talk about today. It’s hard, but it’s by no means impossible, and making this kind of progress is possibly the most valuable work you’ll do in your language studies, because all of it will be specifically tailored to your needs.</p>
<p>The starting point, though, is to identify your current status. What can you do? You don’t (necessarily) need to take a formal language certification test to get a grade, though that can sometimes be useful. The kind of measurements you want to take are more subjective. You want to take stock of your capacity in certain situations, what level you are able to achieve in different contexts (your skills in reading will be different from writing vs listening or speaking, for example) and you want also to assess your experience on the cultural level as well – i.e.&nbsp;how much experience do you have navigating all the unspoken parts of culture, whether that is body language, or behaviours and so on.</p>
<section id="principles-of-skill-acquisition" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="principles-of-skill-acquisition">Principles of Skill Acquisition</h2>
<p>Now a slight detour into some more general principles of skill acquisition. Some of this is derived from my own personal experience, other parts from interviews with experts in this field (such as <a href="http://www.sourcesandmethods.com/podcast/2016/6/14/sources-and-methods-27-k-anders-ericsson">my conversation with K. Anders Ericsson</a>, who more or less <em>invented</em>&nbsp;the field of expert performance studies), and other parts still from reading a bunch of books on the subject.</p>
<p>Three things are relevant here:</p>
<section id="stretch" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="stretch">1) Stretch</h3>
<p>When you’re learning a new skill, you want to step outside your comfort zone. This is usually difficult work, and work that is mentally (and possibly emotionally) taxing. Thus, if you want to get better at speaking in Arabic, you’ll need to speak more, but at the beginning this practice (i.e.&nbsp;talking with other people) will feel pretty horrible, simply because you’re not used to doing it. It’s a paradox that you need to do the thing to get better at doing the thing. It is this difficulty, pushing yourself a little past what you’re capable of doing, that allows for personal growth. (<a href="http://www.alexstrick.com/blog/existential-battles-climbing-amman">I wrote about this</a> in an entirely different context a few weeks ago with respect to my attempts to get better at climbing.)</p>
</section>
<section id="lots-of-practice-coupled-with-speedy-feedback" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="lots-of-practice-coupled-with-speedy-feedback">2) Lots of practice coupled with speedy feedback</h3>
<p>These two parts (practice and feedback) go together. It isn’t practice alone that will allow you to improve, but rather the combination of making efforts to use new skills alongside getting some kind of feedback that tells you when you’re getting it wrong vs when you’re not. An implication of this, too, is the reality that this kind of practice is going to involve you making lots of mistakes. This can feel crappy, especially when you’re getting immediate feedback on exactly when this is happening. You need to adopt a flexible mindset, if possible, in which you see the mistakes as indicators of growth rather than as any kind of personal or intellectual failures on your part.</p>
</section>
<section id="know-what-youre-practicing-and-focus-on-that" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="know-what-youre-practicing-and-focus-on-that">3) Know what you’re practicing and focus on that</h3>
<p>This is basically Ericsson’s <a href="http://www.fastcompany.com/3020758/leadership-now/why-deliberate-practice-is-the-only-way-to-keep-getting-better">principle of “deliberate practice”</a>:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“Rather than chilling out in the comfort of skills you’ve already acquired, as an expert-to-be, you’re relentless about heading to the frontier of your abilities. The practice shouldn’t be so difficult that it overwhelms you—that would be depressingly demotivating, but not so easy that you’re unconsciously languishing. In other words, you’re arranging for flow, that space where you’re right at the boundary of your abilities.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>See also this <a href="http://www.fastcompany.com/3020758/leadership-now/why-deliberate-practice-is-the-only-way-to-keep-getting-better">summary</a> of the routines that ‘experts’ tend to have around deliberate practice:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>They can only engage in practice without rest for around an hour.<br>
They practice in the morning with a fresh mind.<br>
They practice the same amount every day, including on weekends.<br>
They only have four to five hours of deliberate practice a day.<br>
If they don’t get enough rest, they can get overtraining injuries or burnout.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If you’re hoping that ‘using the language’ in a general and non-specific way will get you out of your plateau, you’ll be disappointed. It’s perfectly possible to exist in the plateau zone without improvement <em>ad infinitum</em>. If you want to improve at a certain skill, you’ll need to isolate that element and focus on it in a targeted way. This can be vocabulary, or speaking about a certain topic, or even something as small as ‘using conditional sentences’. Whatever it is, you’ll only get better if you concentrate your efforts.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="customisation-your-individual-needs" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="customisation-your-individual-needs">Customisation &amp; Your Individual Needs</h2>
<p>Learning languages at the post-intermediate level will be a different experience from what you are used to in the early stages. Early on, you’re doing a great deal of necessary-but-boring work to learn basic patterns, vocabulary and grammar.</p>
<p>Once you have mastered that, and you can explain yourself in most basic contexts, you reach the point where you have to customise. There’s a great deal of science and research behind this claim. Check out <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PUqME-RTtIs">this talk</a>, by the always stimulating Alexander Arguelles, for an overview of some of that research.</p>
<p>You’ll need to pick which areas you’re most interested in. This is the hard work of advanced language studies – you pick one area or context, conquer it, and then pick another area and repeat. This fulfils the princicle of focus that I mentioned above.</p>
<p>To give an example from my own studies. My current big push for Arabic is to be able to read serious fiction (i.e.&nbsp;short stories and novels written for native speakers). I’ve <a href="http://www.alexstrick.com/blog/2015/9/surviving-middlebury-how-to-get-the-most-out-of-an-arabic-summer-school">written previously</a> that this was a personal goal, but various realities of how modern literature is written really make it hard to take the leap into complex native-reader-level fiction (especially novels). Arab writers like to use many synonyms (for poetic effect, or perhaps as an attempt at pretension?) for words, so when reading I often find myself stuck referring to dictionaries the whole time. Fortunately,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Advanced-Arabic-Literary-Reader-Students/dp/1138828696/ref=mt_paperback?_encoding=UTF8&amp;me=&amp;tag=soumet-20">a new textbook</a> offering graded literature at just that ‘stretch’ level was released recently, which is allowing me an entry point into that world. None of the texts are simplified, and the language is hard and the number of unknown words is pretty large, but it’s not <em>too</em>&nbsp;far down the scale of difficulty.</p>
</section>
<section id="on-making-a-self-study-plan" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="on-making-a-self-study-plan">On Making a Self-Study Plan</h2>
<p>My next post will cover and offer a host of suggestions for resources you can use to get out of this plateau / dead zone. Before you start reading through and diving into things that seem interesting, I’d strongly advise you take the time to figure out your specific goals. “Improve my Arabic” is not a useful goal. It’s too unspecific. Even “improve my spoken Arabic” may not be particularly useful at the intermediate-advanced level. Once you figure out your goal, write it down somewhere. Maybe stick it to your wall or on the inside of your notebook. It’s good to be reminded why we’re doing the work.</p>
<p>Once you have your goal, then you want to set yourself small targeted bursts or challenges to push out into your stretch zone. You don’t want these challenges to feel like you’re straining against the limits of what you are capable. You want it to be just challenging enough that you feel uncomfortable, but not so much that you are constantly questioning yourself and your abilities in any kind of fundamental sense.</p>
<p>The scale of these challenges will be pretty variable, so examples will span a range of tasks from taking a week to learn and read deeply in a niche topic, to something more longer-term (over six months, perhaps) like my modern literature challenge. The characteristic that you need to look for, however, is that you’ll be able to tell when you’re finished with the challenge. Part of defining the goal is finding a specific (and somewhat measurable) definition of what it means to have achieved what you want.</p>
<p>Then the rest of the trick is basically keeping moving, tracking your progress and achievements along the way. There are various ways of doing this, some of which will depend on what else you have done in this regard. You can add in things like <a href="../blog?tag=beeminder">Beeminder</a> to encourage compliance and regularity, or you can do that in other ways.</p>
<p>When I work with people 1-on-1 to learn a language, a lot of what we do is figuring out this kind of ongoing goal setting and progress assessment. (If you want to learn more about this, <a href="http://www.alexstrick.com/language-coaching">click here and read through what I offer</a>).</p>
<p>The next posts will offer a roadmap to the different resources available to the intermediate student of Arabic and some of the ways you can utilise these resources. It won’t be exhaustive, but I’m pretty sure that most will find something of use in them. Feel free to <a href="https://twitter.com/strickvl">get in touch</a> if you have specific things you want me to tackle in terms of skill development in Arabic.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>language</category>
  <category>useful-tools</category>
  <category>study</category>
  <category>learning</category>
  <category>skills</category>
  <category>languages</category>
  <category>arabicintermediateplateau</category>
  <category>arabic</category>
  <guid>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2021-05-26-arabic-language-plateau-principles.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Arthur Samuel and the ‘Frontier of Automation’</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Strick van Linschoten</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2021-05-26-arthur-samuel-and-the-frontier-of-automation.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The use of neural networks / architectures is a powerful pattern, but it’s worth remembering that this pattern is part of the broader category of machine learning. (You can think of ‘deep learning’ as a rebranding of neural networks or what was once more commonly referred to as connectionism).</p>
<p>In a <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/000271626234000103">classic essay</a> published in 1962, an IBM researcher called Arthur Samuel proposed a way to have computers ‘learn’, a different process from how we normally code things up imperatively (see <a href="https://www.alexstrick.com/blog/telling-cats-from-dogs">my previous post</a> for more on this):</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“Suppose we arrange for some automatic means of testing the effectiveness of any current weight assignment in terms of actual performance and provide a mechanism for altering the weight assignment so as to maximise the performance. We need not go into the details of such a procedure to see that it could be made entirely automatic and to see that a machine so programmed would”learn” from its experience”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Within this essay and this quote specifically, we can find some of the key building blocks of machine learning:</p>
<p><img src="https://alexstrick.com/personal/images/2021-05-26-arthur-samuel-and-the-frontier-of-automation/a5d2ca1f4554_ScreenShot_2021-05-26_at_10.41.29.avif" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>We have our inputs (our data) and our weights. Our weights (or the weight assignments) are variables that allow for different configurations and behaviours of our model. Our results are what the computer has assumed based on the weights and the model, and we have some kind of a metric (our performance) to judge whether this model was accurate or not. The computer then updates the weights based on that performance, tweaking it such that it tries to get better performance.</p>
<p>This is a slightly amended version which language or jargon that are more commonly found today. As you might expect would happen, the language used in the 1960s is in many cases different from what gets used today:</p>
<p><img src="https://alexstrick.com/personal/images/2021-05-26-arthur-samuel-and-the-frontier-of-automation/67a0c320e0d2_ScreenShot_2021-05-26_at_10.41.37.avif" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The main difference here is that we have some labels which are used to know whether the predictions are correct or not. The loss is a way of measuring the performance of our model that is suited for updating our parameters (that used to be referred to as weights).</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>science</category>
  <category>deep-learning</category>
  <category>statistics</category>
  <category>machinelearning</category>
  <category>technology</category>
  <category>deeplearning</category>
  <guid>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2021-05-26-arthur-samuel-and-the-frontier-of-automation.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Telling Cats from Dogs</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Strick van Linschoten</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2021-05-26-telling-cats-from-dogs.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>One of the main ways that using neural networks to train models is different from traditional (imperative) programming can be illustrated with a specific task: let’s say you want to use a computer to tell you whether any particular photo you give it is a cat or a dog.</p>
<p>An imperative approach might be to make a mega list of certain kinds of features that cats and dogs have, and try to encode the differences into some kind of list of logical features. But even knowing how to tell the computer how it should recognise those features is a potentially massive project. How would you even go about that?</p>
<p>Instead, with neural network layers, we turn that pattern on its side. Instead of this:</p>
<p><img src="https://alexstrick.com/personal/images/2021-05-26-telling-cats-from-dogs/2e5999af6274_ScreenShot_2021-05-26_at_09.28.57.avif" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>We have something closer to this:</p>
<p><img src="https://alexstrick.com/personal/images/2021-05-26-telling-cats-from-dogs/ea0a106d3a1e_ScreenShot_2021-05-26_at_09.29.07.avif" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>So the neural networks are learning on the basis of data provided to it — you give it a bunch of images which you’ve pre-labelled to say ‘this one is a cat and that one is a dog’ and so on.</p>
<p>If you use transfer learning, too, you even can use a pretrained model (which is already pretty good at recognising features from images). You can then fine-tune that model to get really good at the specific task you need it to do. (Note, that’s exactly what you do in the first chapter of Howard/Gugger’s&nbsp;<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Deep-Learning-Coders-fastai-PyTorch/dp/1492045527/ref=sr_1_1?dchild=1&amp;qid=1621784082&amp;keywords=deep%2525252Blearning%2525252Bfor%2525252Bcoders&amp;tag=soumet-20&amp;sr=8-1">Deep Learning for Coders</a>).</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>deep-learning</category>
  <category>software</category>
  <category>technology</category>
  <category>deeplearning</category>
  <guid>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2021-05-26-telling-cats-from-dogs.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Deep Learning: Best in Show?</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Strick van Linschoten</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2021-05-23-deep-learning-best-in-show.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Deep Learning is an incredibly powerful technology and there are a number of (focused / specific) areas where it already surpasses human-level abilities. Here are some examples:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Translation: If you haven’t been watching closely, the quality of Google Translate translations has really been improved in recent years. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2016/12/14/magazine/the-great-ai-awakening.html">This 2016 story</a> is a little dated, but it explains how they made a big push a few years back and it continues to improve as the technology improves.</li>
<li>X-ray interpretation: In a matter of a few years, the performance of Deep Learning in reading and making diagnoses from x-rays has surpassed top radiology practitioners. See how DeepMind <a href="https://deepmind.com/research/publications/International-evaluation-of-an-artificial-intelligence-system-to-identify-breast-cancer-in-screening-mammography">raised the bar</a> on identifying breast cancer.</li>
<li>Playing Go: Watch <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WXuK6gekU1Y">the AlphaGo documentary</a> if you haven’t already.</li>
<li>Protein Folding: Check out <a href="https://deepmind.com/blog/article/alphafold-a-solution-to-a-50-year-old-grand-challenge-in-biology">AlphaFold</a> from last November, where DeepMind blasted through a notoriously complicated problem in biology.</li>
<li>Colourising images: A former fast.ai student, Jason Antic, made great progress with his work on <a href="https://blog.floydhub.com/colorizing-and-restoring-old-images-with-deep-learning/">DeOldify</a>.</li>
</ol>
<p>The really great thing about the <a href="https://www.fast.ai">fastai</a> course is how it successfully has managed to democratise Deep Learning as a technology. I always enjoy reading about niche areas where specific burning problems were solved because someone took the opportunity to educate themselves.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>coding</category>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>useful-tools</category>
  <category>deep-learning</category>
  <category>technology</category>
  <category>deeplearning</category>
  <guid>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2021-05-23-deep-learning-best-in-show.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 22 May 2021 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Held back by misunderstanding</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Strick van Linschoten</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2021-05-23-held-back-by-misunderstanding.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The field of deep learning seems to have had a rough journey into public consciousness and adoption. In particular, two theoretical misunderstandings lead to funding being pulled and energy and attention moving away from the field:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Minsky/Papert’s book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Perceptrons-Introduction-Computational-Geometry-Expanded/dp/0262631113/ref=sr_1_1?dchild=1&amp;qid=1621785922&amp;keywords=minsky%252Bperceptron&amp;tag=soumet-20&amp;sr=8-1">Perceptrons</a> showed how a neural network using only one layer was unable to learn some critical functions like <code>XOR</code>. Later in the same book, they show how using more layers addresses this problem completely, but for some reason the ‘fix’ to the problem was ignored and people fixated on the problem with using a single layer and its drawbacks.</li>
<li>By the 1980s, many people were using two layers in their neural networks, and while this did solve the problems identified in ‘Perceptrons’ and people were using neural networks to solve real problems, it was unwieldy in that form. Yes, you could theoretically approximate any mathematical function with two layers, but it was impractical and slow to do so. People thought that this meant that the principle was broken, whereas really the misunderstanding was that two layers were just not enough and that the number of layers could continue to increase.</li>
</ol>
<p>These are two key misunderstandings identified by the Howard/Gugger <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Deep-Learning-Coders-fastai-PyTorch/dp/1492045527/ref=sr_1_1?tag=soumet-20&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=deep%25252Blearning%25252Bfor%25252Bcoders&amp;dchild=1&amp;qid=1621784082">short introduction</a> and I’m sure I’ll read more of these in <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Genius-Makers-Mavericks-Brought-Facebook-ebook/dp/B08CD1M43L/ref=sr_1_1?dchild=1&amp;qid=1621785566&amp;keywords=genius%252Bmakers&amp;tag=soumet-20&amp;sr=8-1">Genius Makers</a>. It’s amazing, but not entirely surprising, that a non-generous and unimaginative misreading of the literature could be responsible for such an effective trashing of a research path.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>deep-learning</category>
  <category>academia</category>
  <category>technology</category>
  <category>deeplearning</category>
  <guid>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2021-05-23-held-back-by-misunderstanding.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 22 May 2021 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>PDP: a precursor to modern neural networks?</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Strick van Linschoten</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2021-05-23-pdp-a-precursor-to-modern-neural-networks.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/parallel-distributed-processing-2-vol-set">Parallel Distributed Processing: Explorations in the Microstructure of Cognition</a>, a multi-volume publication by David Rumelhart, James McClelland and the PDP Research Group, was released in 1968 and is recognised as one of the most important works relating to neural networks.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://mitpress.mit.edu/sites/default/files/styles/large_book_cover/http/mitp-content-server.mit.edu%3A18180/books/covers/cover/%3Fcollid%3Dbooks_covers_0%26isbn%3D9780262631129%26type%3D.jpg?itok=-zzHQP5T" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>PDP (1968</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>They lay out eight features necessary to perform what they called ‘parallel distributed processing’ (which I suppose you can think of as a sort of precursor to modern-day deep learning):</p>
<ul>
<li>processing units</li>
<li>a state of activation</li>
<li>an output function for each processing unit</li>
<li>a pattern of connectivity among units</li>
<li>a propagation rule (for propagating what is learned through the network)</li>
<li>an activation rule</li>
<li>a learning rule (where ‘patterns of connectivity are modified by experience’)</li>
<li>an environment in which the system operates</li>
</ul>
<p>I haven’t read the book, and I don’t fully understand all these different pieces, but it isn’t particularly hard to see the pattern of what would later come to be handled by modern-day neural networks in these features. The vocabulary used to describe it is slightly different, but you have the connectivity between neurons, and you have a process through which you update the layers…</p>
<p>This feels like a book that would reward returning to for a proper in-depth read later on in my studies.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>deep-learning</category>
  <category>history</category>
  <category>technology</category>
  <category>deeplearning</category>
  <guid>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2021-05-23-pdp-a-precursor-to-modern-neural-networks.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 22 May 2021 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Removing Barriers: Deep Learning Edition</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Strick van Linschoten</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2021-05-23-removing-barriers-deep-learning-edition.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I’ve been re-reading Jeremy Howard &amp; Sylvain Gugger’s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Deep-Learning-Coders-fastai-PyTorch/dp/1492045527/ref=sr_1_1?sr=8-1&amp;tag=soumet-20&amp;keywords=deep%2Blearning%2Bfor%2Bcoders&amp;dchild=1&amp;qid=1621784082">Deep Learning for Coders with Fastai and PyTorch</a> and I really appreciate the reminder that a lot of barriers to entry into the Deep Learning space can be productively put to one side.</p>
<p>Gatekeepers make four big claims:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>You need lots of maths to use Deep Learning to solve problems</li>
<li>You need lots of data (think prodigious, Google-sized quantities) to use Deep Learning</li>
<li>You need lots of expensive computers and custom hardware to use Deep Learning</li>
<li>You need a PhD, preferably in Maths or Physics or some computation-heavy science</li>
</ol>
<p>Needless to say, it’s not that maths or more data or better hardware isn’t maybe going to help or improve your experience. But to say that if you don’t have those things then you shouldn’t start is also (seemingly) inaccurate or not helpful.</p>
<p>If you are a domain expert in something that has nothing to do with Deep Learning or data science, you probably have a lot of problems that are like low-hanging fruit in terms of your ability to use powerful techniques like Deep Learning to solve them.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>useful-tools</category>
  <category>deep-learning</category>
  <category>software</category>
  <category>education</category>
  <category>technology</category>
  <category>deeplearning</category>
  <guid>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2021-05-23-removing-barriers-deep-learning-edition.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 22 May 2021 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Rosenblatt’s Mark I Perceptron</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Strick van Linschoten</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2021-05-23-rosenblatts-mark-i-perceptron.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I’ve now read a little about Rosenblatt’s Perceptron in two different places: in the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Deep-Learning-Coders-fastai-PyTorch/dp/1492045527/ref=sr_1_1?dchild=1&amp;qid=1621784082&amp;keywords=deep%252Blearning%252Bfor%252Bcoders&amp;tag=soumet-20&amp;sr=8-1">Howard/Gugger Deep Learning book</a>, and also in Cade Metz’ <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Genius-Makers-Mavericks-Brought-Facebook-ebook/dp/B08CD1M43L/ref=sr_1_1?sr=8-1&amp;tag=soumet-20&amp;keywords=genius%2Bmakers&amp;dchild=1&amp;qid=1621785566">Genius Makers</a>.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/5/52/Mark_I_perceptron.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The Mark I Perceptron</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Built in 1958, it is usually described as the first machine which was based on the principle of the artificial neutron. It used a single layer in this initial configuration, and even in that simple way you could already see glimpses of where it might go.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, Marvin Minsky and Seymour Papert’s apparently perceptive but also damning <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Perceptrons-Introduction-Computational-Geometry-Expanded/dp/0262631113/ref=sr_1_1?sr=8-1&amp;tag=soumet-20&amp;keywords=minsky%2Bperceptron&amp;dchild=1&amp;qid=1621785922">assessment of the perceptron</a> as a technology without a future ushered in the first of the so-called ‘AI winters’, and the idea of using neural networks was buried for several years.</p>
<p>Thankfully, some ignored the herd and stuck with it.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>coding</category>
  <category>useful-tools</category>
  <category>deep-learning</category>
  <category>technology</category>
  <category>deeplearning</category>
  <guid>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2021-05-23-rosenblatts-mark-i-perceptron.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 22 May 2021 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Small, unexpectedly powerful boxes</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Strick van Linschoten</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2021-05-23-small-unexpectedly-powerful-boxes.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Graphics Processing Units or GPUs are what your computer uses to quickly display your screen. Most computers (desktop or laptop) have one of these, and they are used to good effect to keep the screen refreshed and display everything in effectively realtime speed. The world of gaming is also, perhaps unsurprisingly, quite dependent on fast GPU performance, with Nvidia as the lead provider of these hardware units.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://icdn.digitaltrends.com/image/digitaltrends/geforce-rtx-3080-product-gallery-full-screen-3840-3-1-720x720.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>nvidia gpu</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It was discovered a while back that GPUs are also pretty great at performing certain kinds of computation at incredible speed. Certain calculations which, if you would do them on a standard CPU, would take ages to complete are much faster when run on a GPU. For this reason, they’re the hardware of choice for training deep learning models.</p>
<p>GPUs also happen to be heavily used (for similar reasons) for cryptocurrency mining and accordingly there has been a worldwide shortage for some time. Between the crypto bros and the deep learning practitioners, the price got inflated for a while. Nvidia has made <a href="https://www.digitaltrends.com/computing/nvidia-lite-hash-rate-ampere-cards-crypto-limiter/">some attempts</a> to limit crypto miners from using their hardware, but to inconclusive effect.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>useful-tools</category>
  <category>deep-learning</category>
  <category>technology</category>
  <category>deeplearning</category>
  <guid>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2021-05-23-small-unexpectedly-powerful-boxes.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 22 May 2021 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A basic overview of how to use Handlebars</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Strick van Linschoten</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2020-12-10-a-basic-overview-of-how-to-use-handlebars.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://alexstrick.com/personal/images/2020-12-10-a-basic-overview-of-how-to-use-handlebars/9e8ea59b7c0c_image-asset.avif" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><a href="https://handlebarsjs.com/">Handlebars</a> is a simple templating language that you can use with your JavaScript code. It came somewhat late to the game; Python and Ruby and others had their own templating options for a while.</p>
<p>The problem it is trying to solve is the case where you have a lot of HTML code that you need to create in your JavaScript files, but you don’t want to leave your <code>.js</code> files completely bursting to the seams with HTML.</p>
<p>An example is probably good at this point:</p>
<pre><code>&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;script src="https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/handlebars@latest/dist/handlebars.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script src='handlebarsApp.js'&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Hello, World&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;script id='handlebars1' type='text/x-handlebars'&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        {{{name}}}
        &lt;br&gt;
        {{date}}
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</code></pre>
<p>and here’s the associated JavaScript file:</p>
<pre><code>document.addEventListener('DOMContentLoaded', () =&gt; {
  let script1 = document.querySelector('#handlebars1').innerHTML;

  let obj = {
    "name": "&lt;h2&gt;Henry&lt;/h2&gt;",
    "date": "&lt;i&gt;2020-12-10&lt;/i&gt;",
  };

  let templateScript = Handlebars.compile(script1); // returns a function
  document.body.innerHTML = templateScript(obj);
});</code></pre>
<p>A few points to note from this (simple) example:</p>
<ul>
<li>you include the Handlebars functionality by adding a script that either links to a CDN (as I did above), or you download the file and host that yourself.</li>
<li>in the main HTML file, prior to the JavaScript running, you have the <code>&lt;h1&gt;</code> text (‘Hello World’) which is displayed and you have this <code>&lt;script&gt;</code> block (our ‘template’) which is defined with an <code>id</code> of <code>handlebars1</code>. This just sits here until the JavaScript does something with it.</li>
<li>The template uses both double curly braces (<code>{something1}</code>)and triple curly braces (<code>{{something2}}</code>). Double curly braces means that any HTML values are ‘escaped’ when we pass everything through handlebars for compilation. Triple curly braces means that we don’t escape characters, so the <code>&lt;h2&gt;</code> tag is ‘processed’ and you can see the result of that tag being applied, whereas the <code>&lt;i&gt;</code> tag is not applied and it is just treated as plain text (so you see the markup).</li>
<li>In our JavaScript code, the procedure is as follows:
<ul>
<li>(Make sure the DOM has loaded and is ready for things to start happening)</li>
<li>locate the template in the DOM and the html contained with in (you can either use the <code>.innerHTML</code> property or jQuery’s <code>.html()</code> method on a jQuery object</li>
<li>create the context that you want to pass into this template. this will be an object with keys named as per whatever you used to define your template inside the HTML file.</li>
<li>use <code>Handlebars.compile()</code> (passing in the template’s <code>innerHTML</code>) to get a function that can return HTML text depending on what context we pass into it.</li>
<li>use the returned function from the previous step to get that HTML text, and then do with that what we wish. (We might want to create a new node object and insert it into the DOM somewhere. We might want to replace one of the currently existing nodes and put our compiled HTML there instead).</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>Note also how we have managed to keep our JavaScript file mostly free of HTML code. This allows us to keep the layout and templating work to the HTML file, and our logic for our JavaScript file.</p>
<section id="logic-conditionals" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="logic-conditionals">Logic: Conditionals</h2>
<p>Handlebars <em>does</em> allow us to include some logic in our templates, however. I can add a few lines to my template:</p>
<pre><code>&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;script src="https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/handlebars@latest/dist/handlebars.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script src='handlebarsApp.js'&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Hello, World&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;script id='handlebars1' type='text/x-handlebars'&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        {{{name}}}
        &lt;br&gt;
        {{date}}
        &lt;br&gt;&lt;/br&gt;
        {{#if homework}}
        I love homework.
        {{else}}
        -- No homework today
        {{/if}}
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</code></pre>
<p>In this example I added a conditional if/else statement. I checked there was a <code>homework</code> key on the object that we compiled our HTML with. There wasn’t, so the ‘no homework today’ string was output.</p>
<p>(A Handlebars conditional is false if the property value is <code>false</code>, <code>undefined</code>, <code>null</code>, <code>''</code>, <code>0</code> or an empty array.)</p>
<p>Note that we start the vast majority of these ‘logic’ parts of Handlebars with a <code>#</code> character. <code>{else}</code> is apparently an exception and you shouldn’t include a <code>#</code> in front of that when using it.</p>
</section>
<section id="logic-iteration" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="logic-iteration">Logic: Iteration</h2>
<p>We can also include iteration as part of our Handlebars templates using the <code>{#each}</code> keyword. Here’s the HTML:</p>
<pre><code>&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;script src="https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/handlebars@latest/dist/handlebars.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script src='handlebarsApp.js'&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Hello, World&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;script id='handlebars1' type='text/x-handlebars'&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        {{{name}}}
        &lt;br&gt;
        {{date}}
        &lt;br&gt;&lt;/br&gt;
        {{#if homework}}
        I love homework.
        {{else}}
        -- No homework today
        {{/if}}
        &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;List of people&lt;/h3&gt;
        {{#each people}}
        &lt;p&gt;{{this}}&lt;/p&gt;
        {{/each}}
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</code></pre>
<p>And here’s the associated JavaScript file, updated to include an array as part of the context object:</p>
<pre><code>document.addEventListener('DOMContentLoaded', () =&gt; {
  let script1 = document.querySelector('#handlebars1').innerHTML;

  let obj = {
    "name": "&lt;h2&gt;Henry&lt;/h2&gt;",
    "date": "&lt;i&gt;2020-12-10&lt;/i&gt;",
    "people": [
      "Alex Strick",
      "Hope Riley",
    ],
  };

  let templateScript = Handlebars.compile(script1); // returns a function
  document.body.innerHTML = templateScript(obj);
});</code></pre>
<p>Things to note from this example:</p>
<ul>
<li>We start the iteration with <code>{#each people}</code>, passing in the name of the object property that is iterable</li>
<li>We end the iteration with a closing <code>{/each}</code></li>
<li>the <code>this</code> <em>inside</em> our iteration refers to the individual element that we’re currently on as part of our iteration.</li>
</ul>
<p>If we want to deal with nested values, the <code>as</code> keyword along with <code>|</code> pipes allows us to do what we need. Our HTML runs as follows:</p>
<pre><code>&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;script src="https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/handlebars@latest/dist/handlebars.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script src='handlebarsApp.js'&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Hello, World&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;script id='handlebars1' type='text/x-handlebars'&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        {{{name}}}
        &lt;br&gt;
        {{date}}
        &lt;br&gt;&lt;/br&gt;
        {{#if homework}}
        I love homework.
        {{else}}
        -- No homework today
        {{/if}}
        &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;

        &lt;h3&gt;List of people&lt;/h3&gt;
        {{#each people}}
        &lt;p&gt;{{this}}&lt;/p&gt;
        {{/each}}

        &lt;h3&gt;Agenda&lt;/h3&gt;
        {{#each agenda as |agendaItem name|}}
        &lt;p&gt;{{name}}: {{agendaItem.hobby}} // {{agendaItem.work}}&lt;/p&gt;
        {{/each}}

      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</code></pre>
<p>And our updated JavaScript to include a nested object:</p>
<pre><code>document.addEventListener('DOMContentLoaded', () =&gt; {
  let script1 = document.querySelector('#handlebars1').innerHTML;

  let obj = {
    "name": "&lt;h2&gt;Henry&lt;/h2&gt;",
    "date": "&lt;i&gt;2020-12-10&lt;/i&gt;",
    "people": [
      "Alex Strick",
      "Hope Riley",
    ],
    'agenda': {
      'alex': {
        'hobby': 'swimming',
        'work': 'reading',
      },
      'hope': {
        'hobby': 'dancing',
        'work': 'walking',
      },
    },
  };

  let templateScript = Handlebars.compile(script1); // returns a function
  document.body.innerHTML = templateScript(obj);
});</code></pre>
<p>Note that after using the <code>as</code> keyword and the pipes operators, we specify first the variable name to denote the bottom-level object (<code>agendaItem</code>), and then a variable name to denote the two named keys (i.e.&nbsp;<code>alex</code> and <code>hope</code>). This allows us to use both in the pattern we code in our template.</p>
</section>
<section id="logic-iteration-and-the-with-keyword" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="logic-iteration-and-the-with-keyword">Logic: Iteration and the <code>with</code> keyword</h2>
<p>We can use the <code>with</code> keyword to gain access to object properties. Instead of using the <code>as</code> syntax shown above, we can use <code>with</code> so we don’t need the dot syntax to access those properties. The example is a bit contrived, but you get the idea. The relevant additional section of our HTML file would be:</p>
<pre><code>&lt;h3&gt;Agenda 2&lt;/h3&gt;
{{#each agenda as |__ name|}}
{{#with this}}
&lt;p&gt;{{name}}: {{hobby}} // {{work}}&lt;/p&gt;
{{/with}}
{{/each}}</code></pre>
<p>I use the <code>as</code> syntax here so that we can refer to each individual object’s key, but we wouldn’t always necessarily need to do this.</p>
</section>
<section id="partials-for-more-complex-templating" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="partials-for-more-complex-templating">Partials For More Complex Templating</h2>
<p>We can use partials to include templates within templates. The syntax to include a partial inside a template is to use the <code>&gt;</code> symbol inside a pair of curly braces. For example, our HTML might look like this in a simple case:</p>
<pre><code>&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;script src="https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/handlebars@latest/dist/handlebars.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script src='handlebarsApp.js'&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Title of our Page&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;script id='handlebars1' type='text/x-handlebars'&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        {{&gt; partialTemplate}}
        &lt;ol&gt;
        {{#each names}}
        &lt;li&gt;{{this}}&lt;/li&gt;
        {{/each}}
        &lt;/ol&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/script&gt;

    &lt;script id='partial' type='text/x-handlebars'&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;Job: {{job}}&lt;/h2&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;Year: {{year}}&lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</code></pre>
<p>…and the associated JavaScript would look like this:</p>
<pre><code>document.addEventListener('DOMContentLoaded', () =&gt; {
  let script1 = document.querySelector('#handlebars1').innerHTML;
  let script2 = document.querySelector('#partial').innerHTML;

  let obj = {
    "names": [
      "Alex Strick",
      "Hope Riley",
    ],
    'job': 'fencing',
    'year': 2021,
  };

  let templateScript1 = Handlebars.compile(script1);

  Handlebars.registerPartial('partialTemplate', script2);

  let newNode1 = document.createElement('div');
  newNode1.innerHTML = templateScript1(obj);

  document.body.appendChild(newNode1);
});</code></pre>
<p>Some points worth mentioning here about the two chunks of code above:</p>
<ul>
<li>Our partial looks like any other template when we define it in our HTML file. We might want to distinguish it by giving it a certain <code>id</code>, but otherwise it looks like any other handlebars template, with the same <code>type</code> applied to it.</li>
<li>In order for our partial to be usable as a template-within-a-template, it needs to have a variable name that we can use to reference it. We register this name by using <code>Handlebars.registerPartial()</code>. This method takes two arguments: the name that we’d like to register it under, and the template HTML.</li>
<li>The rest of our code runs as in previous examples mentioned above, with the exception that when it reaches the line of code {{&gt; partialTemplate}}`, this is then converted and passed in to replace the placeholder at this point.</li>
</ul>
<p>You can also define partials in the JavaScript code itself. <a href="https://www.sitepoint.com/a-beginners-guide-to-handlebars/">This website</a> offers an example of that:</p>
<pre><code>Handlebars.registerPartial(
  'partialTemplate',
  '{{language}} is {{adjective}}. You are reading this article on {{website}}.'
);

var context={
  "language" : "Handlebars",
  "adjective": "awesome"
}</code></pre>
<p>This is coupled with the following defined in the HTML file:</p>
<pre><code>{{&gt; partialTemplate website="sitepoint"}} &lt;br&gt;
{{&gt; partialTemplate website="www.sitepoint.com"}}</code></pre>
<p>You can play around with that example <a href="http://codepen.io/SitePoint/pen/BNYZLK">on CodePen</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="closing-thoughts" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="closing-thoughts">Closing Thoughts</h2>
<p>You can play around with Handlebars <a href="http://tryhandlebarsjs.com/">here</a>. I like how it gives you options as to where you want to house logic for a particular website. There are obviously tradeoffs to consider, particularly whether code should be running server-side or client-side and how that might affect speed and loading times.</p>
<p>I will need more practical experience to really unpack the implications of using Handlebars, but I am looking forward to getting to use it with a better sense of control now that I understand the fundamentals.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>coding</category>
  <category>useful-tools</category>
  <category>javascript</category>
  <category>web</category>
  <category>technology</category>
  <category>launchschool</category>
  <guid>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2020-12-10-a-basic-overview-of-how-to-use-handlebars.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2020 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How to use jQuery and Handlebars in your website</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Strick van Linschoten</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2020-12-10-how-to-use-jquery-and-handlebars-in-your-website.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>jQuery and Handlebars are both external to the core functionality of JavaScript. Both are libraries that we can use and include when making websites. Doing so is very simple. We include <code>&lt;script&gt;</code>s in the <code>head</code> of our HTML file, as in the following example:</p>
<pre><code>&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;script src="https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/handlebars@latest/dist/handlebars.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script src="https://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/3.5.1/jquery.min.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Hello, World&lt;/h1&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</code></pre>
<p>Note that jQuery is now modular, so you may want to consider whether you want to include the entire library. Above I chose to download it from Google’s CDN, but there are other options listed <a href="https://jquery.com/download/">here</a>.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>coding</category>
  <category>useful-tools</category>
  <category>web</category>
  <category>launchschool</category>
  <category>javascript</category>
  <guid>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2020-12-10-how-to-use-jquery-and-handlebars-in-your-website.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2020 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Using APIs to make things happen on the web</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Strick van Linschoten</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2020-12-04-using-apis-to-make-things-happen-on-the-web.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Towards the end of the Launch School core syllabus, we start to work with API calls. These allow us to pass information between servers. It turns out, this is really useful to be able to do.</p>
<p>Many if not most of the things you do online involve API calls. That little widget on the side of the web page that shows today’s weather: an API call. Even things like Siri which aren’t exactly web pages: using API calls.</p>
<p>Being able to make those calls and to interact with the services available through the internet gives users all sorts of power. The creativity comes, then, in how these things are all combined together.</p>
<p>That said, the dreams of the connected web have been somewhat oversold in the past. What are we on now, web 4.0?.</p>
<p>From a technical perspective, in this part of the course I enjoyed seeing how simple text in the form of JSON objects was behind so much of our communication and interactivity online these days. (All the more reason to have more secure ways of exchanging those plain text data).</p>
<p>I was also conscious of how much creativity and widened thinking has gone into expanding the possibilities of what HTML, CSS and a bit of JavaScript can do over the internet. Some of these capabilities mean that we’re straining the possibilities in this area or that, but above all I take away some inspiration in how people made do with what they had instead of feeling like they needed to reinvent the wheel.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>coding</category>
  <category>javascript</category>
  <category>internet</category>
  <category>web</category>
  <category>technology</category>
  <category>launchschool</category>
  <guid>https://alexstrick.com/personal/2020-12-04-using-apis-to-make-things-happen-on-the-web.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2020 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
